<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Java | Code and Kaizen]]></title>
  <link href="http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/blog/categories/java/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-06T02:40:26+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rafael Huaman]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[info@codeandkaizen.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Java Refresher]]></title>
    <link href="http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/08/20/a-java-refresher/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-20T13:56:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/08/20/a-java-refresher</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first thing I decided to do was to refresh my knowledge of Java and object oriented programming in general. This is probably not the best option for a total beginner. Most of the resources out there that teach Web Dev skills start easy with HTML &amp; CSS as well as web fundamentals. These are great for people who have just started to learn how to code. I am not a beginner though. I am well versed in a lot of technical concepts and I have already been programming for a few years. I just needed to get back in the right mindset. Exploring something familiar would help me do that quickly. So Java it was!</p>

<p>I grabbed a copy of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Head-First-Java-2nd-Edition/dp/0596009208">Head first: Java</a> and started to quickly going through all the concepts. I became very familiar with Java during my college years. But I have been out of practice for a while. Saying that I was a little rusty would be generous. After some reading I started to remember the concepts faster and faster.
The book was very unique. It tries to keep you interested by not being a conventional &ldquo;boring&rdquo; book, so it throws pictures at you and keeps you &ldquo;off balance&rdquo; by not following a conventional form. In short, I liked it and if I ever need to reference some Java concepts again I would probably pick it up one more time.</p>

<p>I did not read the whole book. I did not focus on syntax but I did pay a lot of attention to the sections that involved Object Oriented Programming concepts and good practices. I also went to <a href="http://codingbat.com/">CodingBat.com</a> to practice some basic concepts like recursion and solve some puzzles. This was good enough for me and I decided I was ready to move on.
I thought about starting a bigger project like a simple Android App as a way to practice some more. This was very tempting. The idea of building an App sounded very appealing and fun. Nevertheless, I decided to remain focused and stick to roadmap and topics I laid out.</p>

<p>Next: HTML and CSS</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
