<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: cloud based ide | Code and Kaizen]]></title>
  <link href="http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/blog/categories/cloud-based-ide/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-24T06:05:15+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rafael Huaman]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[info@codeandkaizen.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nitrous.io and How I Stopped Carrying Two Laptops]]></title>
    <link href="http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/12/12/nitrous-dot-io-and-how-i-stopped-carrying-two-laptops/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-12T05:54:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/12/12/nitrous-dot-io-and-how-i-stopped-carrying-two-laptops</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is bittersweet.</p>

<p>Not too long ago I wrote about how <a href="/blog/2013/10/06/my-ubuntu-laptop/">I breathed new life to my old college laptop</a> by turning it into my development/learning computer. When I was done, I was happy. I started using it all the time and even bringing with me when I traveled for work which meant carrying two laptops. I did not care though. My Ubuntu laptop was worth it!</p>

<p>This lasted about two months. A few weeks ago I attended a programming workshop at Full Stack Academy. We spent a few hours working through a few exercises in JavaScript and sharing our solutions. The workshop was good and the instructors were fun; however, they showed me one thing that changed my life. They introduced me to <a href="https://www.nitrous.io/">nitrous.io</a>. Nitrous.io is cloud based development environment with a web-based IDE and cloud VMs. What does this mean? You get a Linux box in your browser (Mind blown!). Maybe I am little late to the party but this literally changed my life. I do not carry two laptops when I travel for work anymore. I travel weekly so this is huge for me.</p>

<p>I recently transferred all my projects to nitrous.io (this blog too!) and life has been much easier that way (Sweet!).</p>

<p>My old laptop is still awesome but I don&rsquo;t use it that much and is back to collecting dust (Bitter!).</p>

<p>Anyway&hellip; cloud based IDEs are the <strong>future</strong>! In fact a quick google search just confirmed that you can use the <a href="http://www.raspberrypi.org/phpBB3/viewtopic.php?t=9984">Raspberry Pi</a> and <a href="https://c9.io/">Cloud9</a> &ndash; another popular web based IDE &ndash; to get a development environment for $35. This is extremely exciting.</p>

<p>That is all for now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
