<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: blog | Code and Kaizen]]></title>
  <link href="http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/blog/categories/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-15T17:33:34-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rafael Huaman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Roadmap to the Full Stack]]></title>
    <link href="http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/08/15/roadmap-to-the-full-stack/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-15T17:25:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/08/15/roadmap-to-the-full-stack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After some research I have narrowed down the list of technologies and topics that a junior web developer should know. To put this list together I researched the technologies that the leading web development shops are using, the curricula offered at several popular Web Dev. workshops, and different posts on the web with advice related to this subject.  I am very familiar with several of these concepts; however, I plan spend some time on all of them, I want to be thorough.</p>

<h2>The Stack</h2>


<ul>
<li>Basic programming concepts</li>
<li>the Ruby programming language</li>
<li>Rails, the framework to develop web application with Ruby</li>
<li>Libraries / Ruby Gems</li>
<li>Rspec, Test Driven Development (TDD) or Behavior Driven Development (BDD) methodologies </li>
<li>HTML and CSS, I will try HAML and Sass </li>
<li>JavaScript and jQuery</li>
<li>Database Concepts</li>
<li>Web basics - forms, HTTP request / response </li>
<li>UNIX command line and development environment</li>
<li>Deployment and Server Management</li>
<li>Git and Github, Source code version control systems</li>
<li>Object Oriented Programming (OOP) concepts</li>
</ul>




<h2>My resources</h2>


<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.codecademy.com/">Codeacademy</a></li>
<li><a href="http://hackercs.com/">Hackcer CS</a></li>
<li><a href="http://codingbat.com/">CodingBat</li>
<li><a href="https://www.codeschool.com/">Code School</li>
<li><a href="http://teamtreehouse.com/">Treehouse</li>
<li><a href="http://exercism.io/">exercism.io</li>
<li><a href="http://www.pairprogramwith.me/">Pair Program with Me</li>
<li><a href="http://www.meetup.com/hackerhours/">Hacker Hours Meetup</li>
<li><a href="http://www.codetriage.com/">Code Triage</li>
<li><a href="http://prework.flatironschool.com/">Flatiron School</li>
</ul>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Start of The Great Web Development Adventure of 2013]]></title>
    <link href="http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/08/10/the-start-of-the-great-web-development-adventure-of-2013/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-10T17:24:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/08/10/the-start-of-the-great-web-development-adventure-of-2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you like my title? I like my goals and projects to sound <strong>EPIC</strong>!</p>

<p>Several weeks ago I decided I wanted to become a full-fledged web developer. After reading about agile development, TDD, and the tools and languages that developers were using nowadays, I got very interested in the subject.
I made this decision after analyzing what I really liked doing professionally. It took me a couple of years of being in the workforce to really see what options were available to me and to learn what type of job I liked. Being a technology consultant helped with this because I was exposed to many different companies and wore several different throughout multiple projects.</p>

<p>Here is the breakdown:</p>

<ul>
<li>I like Building things.</li>
<li>I like programming. At work, I enjoy tasks that involved coding.</li>
<li>I like programming applications over to process automation or database management.</li>
</ul>


<p>
So it turns out, I want to be programming all day, building applications and solving problems with code.
In the next few weeks I will document my progress as I teach myself the skills necessary to be a web developer. Let the adventure begin!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Post]]></title>
    <link href="http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/08/08/first-post/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-08T17:22:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/08/08/first-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am Rafael.</p>

<p>Welcome to my new blog. Here I will post about my attempts to learn new things and improve myself. I figured that writing about my learning experiences will be a good way to reflect on what I learned and at the same time document my progress.</p>

<p>A little about me:</p>

<p>I am technology consultant out of New York City. I have been working in the financial industry helping companies improve their regulatory processes through technology.</p>

<ul>
<li>I flew 100,000 miles last year.</li>
<li>I am from Lima, Peru. I lived there until I was 17.</li>
<li>I graduated from the University of Richmond with a BS in Computer Science and Mathematical Economics</li>
<li>I like books, comics, movies, and video games. </li>
<li>I have played every generation of Pokémon games.  ಠ_ಠ  </li>
<li>I like tennis but I don't watch sports.</li>
<li>I prefer non-fiction to fiction books.</li>
</ul>


<p>And&hellip;</p>

<p>I love <a href="http://www.instructables.com/">building</a>, <a href="http://www.radiolab.org/">learning</a>, <a href="http://hackaday.com/">hacking</a>, <a href="http://www.codeacademy.com/">programming</a>, and <a href="http://www.lifehacker.com">optimizing my life</a>. These last five things are my reason for creating this blog, so you will most likely find posts about them.</p>

<p>That is all for now. Introduction done!</p>

<p>Please comment! I love suggestions and ideas. Please include sources or examples when available.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
