<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: git | Code and Kaizen]]></title>
  <link href="http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/blog/categories/git/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-22T21:22:14-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rafael Huaman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Thoughts on Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/09/19/my-thoughts-on-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-19T23:25:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/09/19/my-thoughts-on-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Originally I wanted to dedicate an entire post to <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> and how I set it up. However, in the interested of moving forward I will just write down my thoughts on it and my experience so far.
When I made the decision to document my learning progress and put it on the internet, I thought I was going to use a simple blog tool like <a href="http://wordpress.com/"> Wordpress</a> or <a href="http://www.blogger.com/home">Blogger</a>. I was almost ready to build my site using one of those tools when I stumbled on to a blog which influenced my own: <a href="http://learnwithjeff.com/">learnwithjeff</a>. In his blog, Jeff mentioned how he learns by teaching and he documents his learning process as well as assigns exercises for those who want to learn along with him.
At the bottom of his page, I saw a little label that said &ldquo;Powered by Octopress&rdquo;. I had never heard of Octopress but I was curious. I looked it up and after reading the tagline &ldquo;A blogging framework for hackers&rdquo; I decided to give it shot. I figured that blogging using a tool meant for &ldquo;hackers&rdquo; would make me a better programmer and would expose me to more technologies.
I was not disappointed. Octopress was easy to setup but in order to get it working and see it live I had to install <a href="https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/">Ruby</a> and <a href="http://git-scm.com/">git</a> on my PC and get <a href="https://www.heroku.com/">Heroku</a> account. This exercise alone exposed me to several new technologies and basically broke the ice. &ldquo;Heroku&rdquo; stopped being a mysterious word I had heard when reading about web development and Git became more approachable. This gave me more confidence to keep moving forward and continue learning. I was making progress and I was happy about it.
After a few searches I settled on a theme I liked and I was done!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Git and Github]]></title>
    <link href="http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/09/19/git-and-github/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-19T23:25:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://codeandkaizen.herokuapp.com/blog/2013/09/19/git-and-github</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is pretty straight forward. I had setup a <a href="https://github.com/">Github</a> account in the past. But I had rarely used it. I used the free <a href=” the http://try.github.io/levels/1/challenges/1”>Try git tutorial</a> from <a href=” http://www.codeschool.com/”>Code School</a> to help me started. I started using git with <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> and with <a href="http://ruby.railstutorial.org/">Michael Hartl&rsquo;s Rails tutorial</a>.
I have started using git to version all of the code I am writing. Additionally, I have been uploading all the code I have completed from tutorials to Github.
The interesting thing about uploading code to Github is that it forced me to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Code_refactoring">refactor</a> and make my code nicer. The thought that my code was out there for everyone to see, made me push myself to make it better!
I have used only few of the features Git and Github have to offer. I use it for code versioning mostly.Additionally, <a href="http://git-scm.com/book/en/Git-Branching">branching</a> is a useful feature that I have started to understand. With some discipline and practice I will introduce branching to my everyday coding. However, this is only the tip of the iceberg in terms of Git. Anyone interested in learning more should check out <a href=http://git-scm.com/book> the Pro Git book</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
